<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Wayland.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Compositors">
  <title>Types of Compositors</title>
  <section id="sect-Compositors-System-Compositor">
    <title>System Compositor</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    ties in with graphical boot
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    hosts different types of session compositors
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    lets us switch between multiple sessions (fast user switching,
	    secure/personal desktop switching)
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    multiseat
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    linux implementation using libudev, egl, kms, evdev, cairo
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    for fullscreen clients, the system compositor can reprogram the
	    video scanout address to source from the client provided buffer.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Compositors-Session-Compositor">
    <title>Session Compositor</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    nested under the system compositor.  nesting is feasible because
	    protocol is async, roundtrip would break nesting
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    gnome-shell
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    moblin
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    compiz?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    kde compositor?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    text mode using vte
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    rdp session
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    fullscreen X session under wayland
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    can run without system compositor, on the hw where it makes
	    sense
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    root window less X server, bridging X windows into a wayland
	    session compositor
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Compositors-Embedding-Compositor">
    <title>Embedding Compositor</title>
    <para>
      X11 lets clients embed windows from other clients, or lets client copy
      pixmap contents rendered by another client into their window.  This is
      often used for applets in a panel, browser plugins and similar.
      Wayland doesn't directly allow this, but clients can communicate GEM
      buffer names out-of-band, for example, using d-bus or as command line
      arguments when the panel launches the applet.  Another option is to
      use a nested wayland instance.  For this, the wayland server will have
      to be a library that the host application links to.  The host
      application will then pass the wayland server socket name to the
      embedded application, and will need to implement the wayland
      compositor interface.  The host application composites the client
      surfaces as part of it's window, that is, in the web page or in the
      panel.  The benefit of nesting the wayland server is that it provides
      the requests the embedded client needs to inform the host about buffer
      updates and a mechanism for forwarding input events from the host
      application.
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    firefox embedding flash by being a special purpose compositor to
	    the plugin
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
