<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Wayland.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Protocol">
  <title>The Wayland Protocol</title>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Basic-Principles">
    <title>Basic Principles</title>
    <para>
      The wayland protocol is an asynchronous object oriented protocol.  All
      requests are method invocations on some object.  The request include
      an object id that uniquely identifies an object on the server.  Each
      object implements an interface and the requests include an opcode that
      identifies which method in the interface to invoke.
    </para>
    <para>
      The server sends back events to the client, each event is emitted from
      an object.  Events can be error conditions.  The event includes the
      object id and the event opcode, from which the client can determine
      the type of event.  Events are generated both in response to requests
      (in which case the request and the event constitutes a round trip) or
      spontaneously when the server state changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    State is broadcast on connect, events are sent
	    out when state changes. Clients must listen for
	    these changes and cache the state.
	    There is no need (or mechanism) to query server state.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The server will broadcast the presence of a number of global objects,
	    which in turn will broadcast their current state.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Code-Generation">
    <title>Code Generation</title>
    <para>
      The interfaces, requests and events are defined in
      <filename>protocol/wayland.xml</filename>.
      This xml is used to generate the function prototypes that can be used by
      clients and compositors.
    </para>
    <para>
      The protocol entry points are generated as inline functions which just
      wrap the <function>wl_proxy_*</function> functions.  The inline functions aren't
      part of the library ABI and language bindings should generate their
      own stubs for the protocol entry points from the xml.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Wire-Format">
    <title>Wire Format</title>
    <para>
      The protocol is sent over a UNIX domain stream socket.  Currently, the
      endpoint is named <systemitem class="service">\wayland</systemitem>,
      but it is subject to change.  The protocol is message-based.  A
      message sent by a client to the server is called request.  A message
      from the server to a client is called event.  Every message is
      structured as 32-bit words, values are represented in the host's
      byte-order.
    </para>
    <para>
      The message header has 2 words in it:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The first word is the sender's object id (32-bit).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The second has 2 parts of 16-bit.  The upper 16-bits are the message
	    size in bytes, starting at the header (i.e. it has a minimum value of 8).The lower is the request/event opcode.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      The payload describes the request/event arguments.  Every argument is always
      aligned to 32-bits. Where padding is required, the value of padding bytes is
      undefined. There is no prefix that describes the type, but it is
      inferred implicitly from the xml specification.
    </para>
    <para>

      The representation of argument types are as follows:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>int</term>
	  <term>uint</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The value is the 32-bit value of the signed/unsigned
	      int.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>string</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Starts with an unsigned 32-bit length, followed by the
	      string contents, including terminating NUL byte, then padding to a
	      32-bit boundary.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>object</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      32-bit object ID.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>new_id</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The 32-bit object ID.  On requests, the client
	      decides the ID.  The only events with <type>new_id</type> are
	      advertisements of globals, and the server will use IDs below
	      0x10000.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>array</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Starts with 32-bit array size in bytes, followed by the array
	      contents verbatim, and finally padding to a 32-bit boundary.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>fd</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The file descriptor is not stored in the message buffer, but in
	      the ancillary data of the UNIX domain socket message (msg_control).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Interfaces">
    <title>Interfaces</title>
    <para>
      The protocol includes several interfaces which are used for
      interacting with the server.  Each interface provides requests,
      events, and errors (which are really just special events) as described
      above.  Specific compositor implementations may have their own
      interfaces provided as extensions, but there are several which are
      always expected to be present.
    </para>
    <para>
      Core interfaces:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_display</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      provides global functionality like objecting binding and
	      fatal error events
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_callback</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      callback interface for done events
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_compositor</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      core compositor interface, allows surface creation
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_shm</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      buffer management interface with buffer creation and format
	      handling
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_buffer</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      buffer handling interface for indicating damage and object
	      destruction, also provides buffer release events from the
	      server
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_data_offer</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      for accepting and receiving specific mime types
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_data_source</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      for offering specific mime types
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_data_device</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      lets clients manage drag &amp; drop, provides pointer enter/leave events and motion
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_data_device_manager</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      for managing data sources and devices
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_shell</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      shell surface handling
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_shell_surface</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      shell surface handling and desktop-like events (e.g. set a
	      surface to fullscreen, display a popup, etc.)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_seat</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      cursor setting, motion, button, and key events, etc.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>wl_output</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      events describing an attached output (subpixel orientation,
	      current mode &amp; geometry, etc.) </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Connect-Time">
    <title>Connect Time</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    no fixed format connect block, the server emits a bunch of
	    events at connect time
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    presence events for global objects: output, compositor, input
	    devices
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Security-and-Authentication">
    <title>Security and Authentication</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    mostly about access to underlying buffers, need new drm auth
	    mechanism (the grant-to ioctl idea), need to check the cmd stream?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    getting the server socket depends on the compositor type, could
	    be a system wide name, through fd passing on the session dbus.
	    or the client is forked by the compositor and the fd is
	    already opened.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Creating-Objects">
    <title>Creating Objects</title>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    client allocates object ID, uses range protocol
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    server tracks how many IDs are left in current range, sends
	    new range when client is about to run out.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Compositor">
    <title>Compositor</title>
    <para>
      The compositor is a global object, advertised at connect time.
    </para>
    <para>
      See <xref linkend="protocol-spec-interface-wl_compositor"/> for the
      protocol description.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Surface">
    <title>Surface</title>
    <para>
      Created by the client.
    </para>
    <para>
      See <xref linkend="protocol-spec-interface-wl_surface"/> for the protocol
      description.
    </para>
    <para>
      Needs a way to set input region, opaque region.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Input">
    <title>Input</title>
    <para>
      Represents a group of input devices, including mice, keyboards.  Has a
      keyboard and pointer focus.  Global object.  Pointer events are
      delivered in both screen coordinates and surface local coordinates.
    </para>
    <para>
      See <xref linkend="protocol-spec-interface-wl_seat"/> for the
      protocol description.
    </para>
    <para>
      Talk about:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    keyboard map, change events
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    xkb on wayland
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    multi pointer wayland
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      A surface can change the pointer image when the surface is the pointer
      focus of the input device.  Wayland doesn't automatically change the
      pointer image when a pointer enters a surface, but expects the
      application to set the cursor it wants in response the pointer
      focus and motion events.  The rationale is that a client has to manage
      changing pointer images for UI elements within the surface in response
      to motion events anyway, so we'll make that the only mechanism for
      setting changing the pointer image.  If the server receives a request
      to set the pointer image after the surface loses pointer focus, the
      request is ignored.  To the client this will look like it successfully
      set the pointer image.
    </para>
    <para>
      The compositor will revert the pointer image back to a default image
      when no surface has the pointer focus for that device.  Clients can
      revert the pointer image back to the default image by setting a NULL
      image.
    </para>
    <para>
      What if the pointer moves from one window which has set a special
      pointer image to a surface that doesn't set an image in response to
      the motion event?  The new surface will be stuck with the special
      pointer image.  We can't just revert the pointer image on leaving a
      surface, since if we immediately enter a surface that sets a different
      image, the image will flicker.  Broken app, I suppose.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Output">
    <title>Output</title>
    <para>
      A output is a global object, advertised at connect time or as they
      come and go.
    </para>
    <para>
      See <xref linkend="protocol-spec-interface-wl_output"/> for the protocol
      description.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  laid out in a big (compositor) coordinate system
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  basically xrandr over wayland
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  geometry needs position in compositor coordinate system\
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  events to advertise available modes, requests to move and change
	  modes
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Shared-Object-Cache">
    <title>Shared Object Cache</title>
    <para>
      Cache for sharing glyphs, icons, cursors across clients.  Lets clients
      share identical objects.  The cache is a global object, advertised at
      connect time.
      <programlisting>
        Interface:      cache
        Requests:       upload(key, visual, bo, stride, width, height)
        Events:	        item(key, bo, x, y, stride)
                        retire(bo)
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Upload by passing a visual, bo, stride, width, height to the
	    cache.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Upload returns a bo name, stride, and x, y location of object in
	    the buffer.  Clients take a reference on the atlas bo.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Shared objects are refcounted, freed by client (when purging
	    glyphs from the local cache) or when a client exits.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Server can't delete individual items from an atlas, but it can
	    throw out an entire atlas bo if it becomes too sparse.  The server
	    sends out an <type>retire</type> event when this happens, and clients
	    must throw away any objects from that bo and reupload.  Between the
	    server dropping the atlas and the client receiving the retire event,
	    clients can still legally use the old atlas since they have a ref on
	    the bo.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    cairo needs to hook into the glyph cache, and maybe also a way
	    to create a read-only surface based on an object form the cache
	    (icons).
	    <function>cairo_wayland_create_cached_surface(surface-data)</function>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Protocol-Drag-and-Drop">
    <title>Drag and Drop</title>
    <para>
      Multi-device aware. Orthogonal to rest of wayland, as it is its own
      toplevel object.  Since the compositor determines the drag target, it
      works with transformed surfaces (dragging to a scaled down window in
      expose mode, for example).
    </para>
    <para>
      See <xref linkend="protocol-spec-interface-wl_data_offer"/>,
      <xref linkend="protocol-spec-interface-wl_data_source"/> and
      <xref linkend="protocol-spec-interface-wl_data_offer"/> for
      protocol descriptions.
    </para>
    <para>
      Issues: 
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    we can set the cursor image to the current cursor + dragged
	    object, which will last as long as the drag, but maybe an request to
	    attach an image to the cursor will be more convenient?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Should drag.send() destroy the object?  There's nothing to do
	    after the data has been transferred.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    How do we marshal several mime-types?  We could make the drag
	    setup a multi-step operation: dnd.create, drag.offer(mime-type1),
	    drag.offer(mime-type2), drag.activate().  The drag object could send
	    multiple offer events on each motion event.  Or we could just
	    implement an array type, but that's a pain to work with.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Middle-click drag to pop up menu?  Ctrl/Shift/Alt drag?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Send a file descriptor over the protocol to let initiator and
	    source exchange data out of band?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Action? Specify action when creating the drag object? Ask
	    action?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Sequence of events:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The initiator surface receives a click (which grabs the input
	    device to that surface) and then enough motion to decide that a drag
	    is starting.  Wayland has no subwindows, so it's entirely up to the
	    application to decide whether or not a draggable object within the
	    surface was clicked.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The initiator creates a drag object by calling the
	    <function>create_drag</function> method on the dnd global
	    object.  As for any client created object, the client allocates
	    the id.  The <function>create_drag</function> method also takes
	    the originating surface, the device that's dragging and the
	    mime-types supported.  If the surface
	    has indeed grabbed the device passed in, the server will create an
	    active drag object for the device.  If the grab was released in the
	    meantime, the drag object will be in-active, that is, the same state
	    as when the grab is released.  In that case, the client will receive
	    a button up event, which will let it know that the drag finished.
	    To the client it will look like the drag was immediately cancelled
	    by the grab ending.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    The special mime-type application/x-root-target indicates that the
	    initiator is looking for drag events to the root window as well.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    To indicate the object being dragged, the initiator can replace
	    the pointer image with an larger image representing the data being
	    dragged with the cursor image overlaid.  The pointer image will
	    remain in place as long as the grab is in effect, since the
	    initiating surface keeps pointer focus, and no other surface
	    receives enter events.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    As long as the grab is active (or until the initiator cancels
	    the drag by destroying the drag object), the drag object will send
	    <function>offer</function> events to surfaces it moves across. As for motion
	    events, these events contain the surface local coordinates of the
	    device as well as the list of mime-types offered.  When a device
	    leaves a surface, it will send an <function>offer</function> event with an empty
	    list of mime-types to indicate that the device left the surface.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If a surface receives an offer event and decides that it's in an
	    area that can accept a drag event, it should call the
	    <function>accept</function> method on the drag object in the event.  The surface
	    passes a mime-type in the request, picked from the list in the offer
	    event, to indicate which of the types it wants.  At this point, the
	    surface can update the appearance of the drop target to give
	    feedback to the user that the drag has a valid target.  If the
	    <function>offer</function> event moves to a different drop target (the surface
	    decides the offer coordinates is outside the drop target) or leaves
	    the surface (the offer event has an empty list of mime-types) it
	    should revert the appearance of the drop target to the inactive
	    state.  A surface can also decide to retract its drop target (if the
	    drop target disappears or moves, for example), by calling the accept
	    method with a NULL mime-type.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    When a target surface sends an <function>accept</function> request, the drag
	    object will send a <function>target</function> event to the initiator surface.
	    This tells the initiator that the drag currently has a potential
	    target and which of the offered mime-types the target wants.  The
	    initiator can change the pointer image or drag source appearance to
	    reflect this new state.  If the target surface retracts its drop
	    target of if the surface disappears, a <function>target</function> event with a
	    NULL mime-type will be sent.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If the initiator listed application/x-root-target as a valid
	    mime-type, dragging into the root window will make the drag object
	    send a <function>target</function> event with the application/x-root-target
	    mime-type.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    When the grab is released (indicated by the button release
	    event), if the drag has an active target, the initiator calls the
	    <function>send</function> method on the drag object to send the data to be
	    transferred by the drag operation, in the format requested by the
	    target.  The initiator can then destroy the drag object by calling
	    the <function>destroy</function> method.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The drop target receives a <function>data</function> event from the drag
	    object with the requested data.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      MIME is defined in RFC's 2045-2049. A
      <ulink url="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/media-types/">
      registry of MIME types</ulink> is maintained by the Internet Assigned
      Numbers Authority (IANA).
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
