<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="aura_shell">

  <copyright>
    Copyright 2017 The Chromium Authors.

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zaura_shell" version="1">
    <description summary="aura_shell">
      The global interface exposing aura shell capabilities is used to
      instantiate an interface extension for a wl_surface object.
      This extended interface will then allow the client to use aura shell
      specific functionality.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="aura_surface_exists" value="0"
	     summary="the surface already has an aura surface object associated"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="get_aura_surface">
      <description summary="extend surface interface for aura shell">
	Instantiate an interface extension for the given wl_surface to
	provide aura shell functionality. If the given wl_surface is not
	associated with a shell surface, the shell_surface_missing protocol
	error is raised.
      </description>

      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zaura_surface"
	   summary="the new aura surface interface id"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
	   summary="the surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zaura_surface" version="1">
    <description summary="aura shell interface to a wl_surface">
      An additional interface to a wl_surface object, which allows the
      client to access aura shell specific functionality for surface.
    </description>

    <enum name="frame_type">
      <description summary="different frame types">
	Frame types that can be used to decorate a surface.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0" summary="no frame"/>
      <entry name="normal" value="1" summary="caption with shadow" />
      <entry name="shadow" value="2" summary="shadow only"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="set_frame">
      <description summary="request a frame for surface">
	Suggests a surface should use a specific frame.
      </description>
      <arg name="type" type="uint" summary="the new frame type"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

</protocol>
