<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE bookinfo PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Wayland.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<bookinfo id="book-Wayland-Wayland">
  <title>Wayland</title>
  <subtitle>The Wayland display server</subtitle>
  <productname>Documentation</productname>
  <productnumber>0.1</productnumber>
  <edition>1</edition>
  <pubsnumber>0</pubsnumber>
  <abstract>
    <para>
      Wayland is a protocol for a compositor to talk to
      its clients as well as a C library implementation of
      that protocol. The compositor can be a standalone
      display server running on Linux kernel modesetting
      and evdev input devices, an X application, or a
      wayland client itself. The clients can be
      traditional applications, X servers (rootless or
      fullscreen) or other display servers.
    </para>
  </abstract>
  <corpauthor>
    <inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/wayland.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>
          Wayland logo
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
  </corpauthor>

  <legalnotice lang="en-US">
    <para>
      Copyright <trademark class="copyright"></trademark> &YEAR; &HOLDER;
    </para>

    <para>
      Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
      software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
      without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
      all copies and that both that copyright notice and this
      permission notice appear in supporting documentation, and that
      the name of the copyright holders not be used in advertising or
      publicity pertaining to distribution of the software without
      specific, written prior permission.  The copyright holders make
      no representations about the suitability of this software for
      any purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
      warranty.
    </para>

    <para>
      THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO
      THIS SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
      MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
      HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL
      DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE,
      DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR
      OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE
      USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
    </para>
  </legalnotice>


  <xi:include href="Author_Group.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</bookinfo>
